“90年代初是印度的变革时代”
[Sucheta] 'Early 1990's. The era of change for India.'
"旧的英雄已经成为历史，新的英雄正在崛起"
'The old heroes were gone, and the new ones were yet to rise.'
"在手机、互联网和社交媒体出现之前..."
'Before the time of mobiles, internet and social media...'
“ ... 一切都以自己缓慢的步伐前进”
'...everything moved at its own sweet pace.'
“无论是国家的经济... ... ”
'Be it the economy of the country...'
"或是政府办公室的文书工作"
'...or the paperwork at government offices...'
"甚至还有突发新闻"
'...and even breaking news.'
"如果要说飞速发展的，那也只有孟买证券交易所"
'If there was speed, it was only at the Bombay Stock Exchange.'
“那是普通人第一次...”
'For the first time, the common man...'
"试图通过股票市场改变自己的命运"
'...was trying to change his fate through the share market.'
"在这个闪闪发光的股票市场..."
'And in this glittering share market...'
“ ... 每个人都被利润的承诺蒙蔽了双眼”
'...everyone was blinded by the promise of profit.'
一个如此伟大的承诺，甚至隐藏了承诺背后善意的谎言
'A promise so great, that it hid the white lies on which it was based.'
"终于那一天来临了，动摇了印度经济的根基"
'And then came the day, which shook the very foundation of the Indian economy.'
“但那一天的故事，开始于它的前一天”
'But the story of that fateful day starts a day earlier.'
先生! 打扰一下，先生
Sir! Excuse me, sir.
先生，我要见编辑，非常紧急，先生
Sir, I need to meet the editor. It's very urgent, sir.
哦，您叫什么名字？
Oh, your good name?
先生，我是来自SBI（印度国家银行）的沙拉德·贝拉里
Sir, I'm Sharad Bellary from S- SBI.
我知道了
I see.
先生，我有一些机密信息
Sir, I have some confidential information.
那么，你想见哪位编辑呢？
So, which editor would you like to meet?
主编? 城市编辑? 体育编辑? 商业编辑？
Executive editor? City editor? Sports editor? Business editor?
- 先生，任何编辑都可以...-副编辑？
- Sir, any editor will do... - Associate editor?
我没多少时间了，长官
I don't have much time, Sir.
如果时间被浪费掉，我的情报就过期了
If it is wasted, my information will turn stale.
先生，也许我可以把情报直接给你
Sir, maybe I can give it to you...
- 你看起来也像个高级编辑-不不
- You look like a senior editor yourself. - Oh, no, no...
我只是个普通人
I'm just a common man, you see.
- 先生，你是... 你是...-我是R.K. 拉克斯曼
- Sir, you are... you are... - Yes... R.K. Laxman. Yeah.
- 看来你的消息很重要 -是的，先生
- It seems your news is very important. - Yes, sir.
我想你应该见见商业编辑基兰·  阿杰冈卡先生
I think you should meet the business editor, Mr. Kiran Ajgaonkar.
‘是的，我去那里是为了出版是的，我去了那里’
[Kiran] 'Yes, I'm there for the edition. Yes, I'm there.'
我再打给你，拉克西曼先生？
Oh! I'll call you back. Laxman sir?
基兰，有人来找你
Kiran, someone is looking for you.
您怎么亲自过来了，先生? 您可以找人代劳的
Why did you take the trouble, sir? You could've asked a peon.
- 没关系，请坐-谢谢，先生
- Oh, it's alright. Please. - Thank you, sir.
- 你好，先生-告诉我，我能为你做什么？
- Hello, sir. - Tell me, how can I help you?
你要喝什么? 茶? 咖啡? 水？
What will you have? Tea? Coffee? Water?
不，谢谢，先生 印度国家银行内部有个大问题，先生
No, thank you, sir. There is a huge problem at SBI, sir.
这是个巨大的骗局，你必须知道，先生
It's a very big fraud. You need to know about it, sir.
- 骗局? 发生在国家银行?-是的，先生
- Fraud? At SBI? - Yes, sir.
继续
Go on.
先生，银行开出了一张没有银行收据的支票
Sir, the bank has issued a cheque without any BR.
银行收据，先生
- BR? - Bank receipt, sir.
银行收据
Oh, bank receipt.
长官，这张支票没有在任何明细账中记载
Sir, there is no SGL note either.
在公共债务办公室中，账上也没有计数
In the PDO, the books aren't tallying.
这是个大问题，长官
It's a big problem, sir.
明细账?公共债务办公室？
SGL? PDO?
先生，SGL 是明细账
Sir, SGL is Subsidiary General Ledger...
PDO 是印度储备银行的公共债务办公室
...and PDO is Public Debt Office, sir. Of the RBI.
所以，如果没有明细账或银行收据，那么..
So, if you don't get the SGL or BRs then...
- 等一下等一下-这是..
- One second. Wait a minute. - It's a...
这对我来说太专业了
This is getting too technical for me.
我会把你送到一个能理解的人那里
I'll send you to someone who will understand this.
- 等一下-好的，请快点先生
- Just a second. - Okay. Please hurry, sir.
请把他带到苏切塔女士的办公室
Please take him to Sucheta ma'am.
谢谢，先生，谢谢
Thank you, sir. Thank you.
来吧，先生，我们走
Come on, sir. Let's go.
"你应该早上亲自通知我”
[Sucheta] 'You should have informed me in the morning itself.'
你可以在证券交易所给我打电话
'You could've called me from BSE.'
抱歉，苏切塔
Sorry, Sucheta.
- 关于罢工有些混乱...-我该怎么处理这个？
-There was confusion regarding the strike... - What am I going to do with this sorry?
我们之所以报道这件事，是因为我们认为罢工已经结束了，对吗？
We've only run this story because we assumed that the strike was getting over, right?
我是说... 每次你来找我的时候，阿狄提亚
I mean... every time with you, Aditya.
我们不可能做同样的事情，对吧？
We can't be doing the same thing, right?
- 应该有一些...-苏切塔女士
- There should be some... -[Peon] 'Sucheta ma'am.'
基兰先生让他来见你
Kiran sir has sent him to meet you.
- 沙拉德·贝拉里，来自...-请坐
- Sharad Bellary from S... - Please be seated.
马扬克? ，我要你去交易所，从马努 · 蒙德拉那里得到一份关于罢工的声明
Mayank? I need you to go to BSE and get a statement from Manu Mundra about the strike.
我需要知道是什么突然改变了
I need to know what changed so suddenly.
好吧，我是不是也应该和我的其他消息来源谈谈？
Fine. Should I also talk to a couple of my other sources there?
是的，但是请不要在那里说闲话
Yeah. But please don't start gossiping there.
我需要尽快发稿，好吗？
I need to file this ASAP, yeah?
还有你们，请尊重最后期限，好吗？
And you guys, please start respecting deadlines, yeah?
我的意思是我们不能一次又一次逾期，对吗？
I mean we can't keep doing this again and again, right?
- 是的，你说吧 -什么
- Yes, tell me. -[Bellary] 'Sorry?'
说吧？
Tell me?
是的，必须守时
Yes. Deadlines must be respected. Correct.
不，我是说，告诉我你为什么在这里？
No. I mean, tell me why are you here?
哦，好的，夫人
Oh, yes, ma'am.
- 我是沙拉德·贝拉里来自...
- I'm Sharad Bellary from S... -[phone rings]
请稍等，失陪一下
Just one minute, please. Excuse me.
喂? 拉维，我不能和你一起参加印度斯坦有限公司的会议了
Hello? Ravi, I won't be able to do the Hindustan Limited conference with you.
不我只是... 等一下
No, I just... Hold on a second.
- 你要喝茶吗? 请给我一杯茶-茶? 不要
- Would you like some tea? Organise a cup of tea, please. - Tea? No.
是的，不，罢工的事情还在进行中，所以，我需要集中精力
Yeah. No, the strike thing is still developing. So, I need to focus on that.
好的谢谢
Yeah. Thanks.
谢谢，回头再聊，再见
Thanks, I'll talk to you later. Bye.
- 是的，所以...-对不起，只是..
- Yeah, so... -[Sucheta] 'Sorry, just...'
喂? 我早上要的是黄油面包
Hello? I had asked for a buttered bun in the morning.
我现在不想要，现在是午餐时间
I don't want it now. It's lunchtime.
不，待会儿再说，谢谢
No. Later. Thank you.
- 你还没喝茶? 阿狄提亚?-夫人，我..
- You didn't get your tea? Aditya? - Ma'am, I...
- 抱歉-我得走了，夫人，我要迟到了
- Sorry. - I've to go, ma'am. I'm getting late.
- 没人听我说话吗！
- No one listens!
- 我不要茶!-好吧，贝拉里先生，请告诉我
- I don't want tea! - Okay, Mr. Bellary. Please, tell me.
女士，我是来自印度国家银行的沙拉德·贝拉里
Ma'am, I'm Sharad Bellary from SBI.
我来是想告诉你国家银行有些事情非常可疑
I just want to tell you that there's something very fishy going on at SBI.
事情已经不是过去的样子了
Things are not how they used to be.
银行的一切都变了
'Everything has changed at SBI.'
这里真的有些不对劲
There's something really amiss there.
这是一个巨大的丑闻
It's a huge scandal.
你甚至无法想象这个骗局有多大
You can't even begin to imagine how big the fraud is.
骗局？
Fraud?
五十亿卢比
Five hundred crores.
印度国家银行的账目上少了50亿卢比
Five hundred crores are missing from the books of SBI.
付款时没有任何银行收据
Payments have been made without any BRs.
- BR 的意思是...-银行收据，我知道
- BR means... - Bank receipts, I know.
你在国家银行做什么工作? 你在哪个部门？
What do you do at SBI? Which department do you work in?
我在公关部，女士，公共关系
It's PR, ma'am. Public relations.
那你是怎么知道的？
Then, how do you know this?
女士，这已经持续了一段时间了
Ma'am, this has been going on for a while now.
他们每天都开会
They are having meetings upon meetings daily.
但现在情况已经失控了
But things are out of control now.
因为我们甚至都没有收到明细账，女士
Because we didn't even receive the SGL, ma'am.
那么他们要怎么记账呢? 我是说... 我... 我..
How will they show it in the books? I mean... I'm so... I...
- SGL 的意思是...-我知道是明细账
- SGL means... - Subsidiary General Ledger, I know.
所以，印度国家银行已经发放了50亿卢比的资金
So, SBI has issued a payment of 500 crores.
而作为交换的明细账和银行收据还没有收到
And the SGL and BRs due in exchange haven't been received.
你知道自己在说什么，对吧？
You do know what you're saying, right?
五十亿是一个很大的数目，计算器可能都打不全这些数字
Five hundred crore is such a huge amount, even a calculator may shy away from it.
是的，这就是骗局的严重程度，甚至可能更严重
Yes, that's how big the fraud is. Maybe even bigger than that.
你知道谁是这个骗局的幕后黑手是谁吗？
Do you know who is behind this fraud?
“哈... ”
[Bellary] 'Har...'
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔
H-Harshad Mehta, ma'am...
Harshad Mehta.
“这不仅仅是一个关于印度最大金融骗局的故事”
[Sucheta] 'This isn't just a story about India's biggest financial scam.'
这是印度和印度人民的故事
'This is the story of India and her people.'
这是我们的故事，我们梦想的故事
'It's our story, the story of our dreams.'
哈尔沙德 · 梅塔曾经也有过那种梦想
'The kind of dreams that Harshad Mehta lived.'
1992年，哈尔沙德 · 梅塔是印度纳税金额最高的先进纳税人
'In 1992, Harshad Mehta was India's highest advance taxpayer.'
他的个人财产价值400亿卢比
'His personal holdings were worth 4,000 crores.'
这是很大一笔钱，不是吗
'It's a large number, right?'
经过今天的通货膨胀调整... ..
'Adjusted for inflation today...'
这个数字将超过2万亿卢比
'...this number would be over 20,000 crores.'
那么，一个来自中产阶级下层家庭的男孩是如何... ..
'So, how did a boy from a lower middle class family...'
在这么短的时间内赚了这么多钱
'...make so much money, in such a short time?'
哈尔沙德的初恋是板球
'Harshad's first love was cricket.'
他是个优秀的旋转投球手
'He was an excellent spin bowler.'
每个人都认为，如果不是为了印度，他至少会为兰吉杯而战
'Everyone thought, if not for India, he would at least play for the Ranji trophy.'
“他学习成绩很差”
'He was weak in studies.'
因此，他的大学生活就是打板球和跳加尔巴舞
'So, he spent his college life playing cricket and dancing Garba.'
但他父亲失败的布匹生意让他背上了沉重的责任
'But his father's failed cloth business burdened him with responsibilities.'
哈沙德做了很多零活，帮忙打理家务
'Harshad did many odd jobs, to help run the house.'
“他做职员，工资是六百卢比... ... ”
'Sometimes, he worked as a clerk for a six hundred rupee salary...'
’ ... 其他时间，他试图销售塑料，水泥，钻石等’
'...at other times, he tried selling plastic, cement, diamonds etc.'
但是钱永远不够
'But the money was never enough.'
因为哈沙德的梦想远远大于这微薄的收入
'Because Harshad's dreams were much bigger than this small income.'
“责任越来越重，哈沙德的不安也越来越重”
'Responsibilities were increasing, and so was Harshad's restlessness.'
咖喱茄子做的简直完美
Full marks to the one who has prepared this eggplant curry.
嫂子成功了
Bhabhi has made it.
我是说他的嫂子
His sister-in-law, I mean.
我就没那么幸运了
I'm not so lucky to have one.
兄弟，我要结婚了
Bhai, I will get married.
别再嘲讽了
Enough of these taunts.
乔蒂，真的很好吃
Jyoti, it's really very tasty.
这茄子是不是有点焦了？
Isn't the eggplant a bit burnt?
似乎只有你有这么认为
Only you seem to feel that.
你最好小心点，不然她下一个就会把你煮了一定要把他捣烂
Better watch out or she'll cook you next. Make sure that you mash him well.
- 乔蒂，过来和我们一起吃饭-好的
- Jyoti, come, eat with us. - Yes.
没关系，我一会儿再吃
It's alright, I will eat later.
- 来吧，我们完了-来吧，我也完了
- Come. We're done. - Come on. I am done too.
来，我们吃点烤面包
Come, let's have some paan.
- 我要一个普通的...-我知道，爸爸
- I'll have a plain one... - I know, Pappa.
- 不要槟榔对吧?-对的
- Without areca, right? - Done.
茄子真的很好吃，对吧？
The eggplant was really good, right?
我们还能这样生活多久？
How long will we live like this?
什么意思？
What do you mean?
我说的是房子
I'm talking about the house.
感觉像是上下班高峰期的火车
It feels like a rush-hour train.
如果再这样继续下去，我们很快就会开始互相拳打脚踢
If this continues, we'll soon be punching and elbowing each other.
兄弟，这种困难将会持续下去
Bhai, this difficulty is here to stay.
我想说的是住在这里很艰难
And staying here is difficult. That's what I mean.
听着... 听我的建议..
Look... take my advice...
乔蒂和你应该找一个小房子然后搬走
Jyoti and you should find a small house and shift.
- 附近有间独立的房子-你在说什么？
- A separate house, nearby. - What are you saying?
如果我们要搬走，为什么你们不一起搬家呢？
If we have to shift, why don't we all shift together?
- 我们去找个大房子-大房子？
- Let's find a big house. - Big house?
我们有那么多钱吗? 大房子！
Do we have that much money? Big house!
钱是我们真正的问题
Money is our real problem.
今天，甚至连钻石市场也失去了它的光芒
Today, even the diamond-market has lost its shine.
这次钻石交易不会给我们带来任何好处
This diamond trading will fetch us nothing.
一切都会好起来的
It will. Everything will be okay.
- 慢一点，但是要稳一点-慢一点，慢个屁！
- Slowly, but surely. - Slowly, my foot!
每个人都在忙着做这做那
Everyone is busy doing something or the other.
甚至连小吃店老板都在买车
Even a snack-seller is buying cars...
有些人在纺织品上赚了三倍的利润
...some are making a triple profit in textiles...
每个人的口袋都是满的
Everyone's pockets are full.
看看吉梅什，他在股票市场赚了那么多钱
Look at Jimesh. He has made so much money in the share market.
兄弟，你可以在股票市场上稍稍涉足一下
Bhai, you can dabble a little in the share market.
但我们不能指望这个
But we can't depend on that.
- 太冒险了-什么叫”冒险” ？
- It's too risky. - What do you mean ‘risky'?
吉梅什让他的家人都进入了股票市场
Jimesh has involved his entire family in this business.
甚至他的岳母
Even his mother-in-law.
她不用数还能活几天，而是在数钱
Instead of counting her last days, she's counting money.
兄弟，我们不是吉梅什的岳母
Bhai, we're not Jimesh's mother-in-law.
如果出了什么差错，尚蒂拉尔会在吉梅什的岳母死之前杀了我们
If something goes wrong, Shantilal will kill us before Jimesh's mother-in-law dies.
这将是我们的末日
It'll be the end of us.
吉米什的岳母，他说！
Jimesh's mother-in-law, he says!
冷静地想，我相信一定有办法的
Think calmly. I'm sure there is a way.
- 阿什温?-嗯？
- Ashwin? - Yes?
听我说，你也要结婚
Listen to me. You also get married.
- 你说结婚是什么意思?-为什么不？
- What do you mean, get married? - Why not?
你看到我们房子的大小了吗？
Have you seen the size of our house?
一定会有办法的
I'm sure there is a way.
爸爸，她在说什么？
Pappa, what is she saying?
我妻子睡在哪里? 天花板上吗？
Where will my wife sleep? On the ceiling?
[傻笑]
[giggling]
别笑了，去睡觉吧
Stop laughing. Go to sleep.
- 那就保持单身-好的
- Stay single, then. - Okay.
- 你今天心情不好?-我不该心情不好吗？
- You're in a mood today? - Shouldn't I be?
- 嘿! 大家都睡了-那又怎样？
- Hey! Everyone's asleep. - So?
会吵醒爸爸的！
Pappa will wake up!
这房子很小，风险很大
It's a small house. It's risky.
这房子不会一夜之间变成平房的
Well, this house will not turn into a bungalow overnight.
我们将不得不冒这个险
We will have to take the risk.
无论如何，风险是生活的调味品
And anyway, risk is the spice of life.
叔叔，让一让! 你为什么不把肚子缩小一点！
Uncle, move! Why don't you reduce this paunch!
我对股票市场是认真的
I'm serious about the share market.
- 所以呢?-如果我们做得好就可以赚很多钱
- So? - If we do it right, we can make a lot of money.
当然，确实可以赚钱，但风险同样也很高
Sure we can make money, but it's a risk.
风险是生活的调味品
Risk is the spice of life.
什么？
What?
听着... ... 如果你认识什么人，介绍一下我，我会一头扎进去的
Look... If you know anyone, introduce me. I will dive into it.
好的，但是你有时间吗? 你能处理吗？
Okay, but do you have the time? Can you handle it?
我穷的只剩下时间了
We only have time to spend.
或者我们花时间等待合适的时机
Or we spend ourselves waiting for the right time.
兄弟，这些对话太棒了
Bhai, these dialogues are great.
但事情并没有那么简单
But it's not that easy.
- 再考虑一下吧-我决定了
- Give it a thought. - Done.
- 听着... 你总是...-我已经决定了
- Look... you always... - I've made up my mind.
够了，给我一些甜的泡菜
That's enough. Give me some sweet pickle.
好了没有? 现在让我安静地吃饭可以吗
Are you done? Now let me eat in peace.
在这之前你在哪里工作过吗？
Have you worked anywhere before this?
我一生中做过很多工作，我确信我可以从这里的一个小职员做起
I've done lots of jobs in my life. I'm sure I can start as a jobber here.
- 你不会明白的-为什么？
- You won't understand it. - Why not?
我懂商业，我只是刚刚进入这个市场
I understand business. I'm just new to the market.
对我们古吉拉特人来说，商业比宗教更伟大，对吗？
And for us Gujaratis, business is greater than religion, right?
兄弟，你不一定要博览群书才能成为一个批发商
Bhai, you don't have to be well-read to become a jobber.
甚至那些五年级就辞职的人也在这里做临时工
Even those who quit after the fifth-grade work as jobbers here.
我五年级的时候挂科了，我是说，我考了两次才通过
I failed my fifth grade. I mean, i took two attempts to clear.
给我一些酥油
Give me some ghee.
- 拿起电话-什么？
- Pick up the phone. - Huh?
拿起电话
Pick the phone up.
25-50-37.
仔细听着，我不会重复
Listen carefully. I won't repeat.
一盘bhindi，一盘gatta..
One plate bhindi, one plate gatta...
... rajwadi kadi，jain khichdi，两个 rotis
...rajwadi kadi, jain khichdi, two rotis.
两份薄饼，两份papad，一份烤的，一份炸的，还有酸奶酪
Two bhakri, two papad, one roasted, one fried. And raita.
再来一份洋葱番茄沙拉
Also, an onion-tomato salad.
你好，是的，请点菜
Hello, yes, take an order.
一个盘子 bhindi，一个盘子 gatta，rajwadi kadi..
One plate bhindi, one plate gatta, rajwadi kadi...
... jain khichdi，两个 rotis
...jain khichdi, two rotis.
两份巴克里，两份帕帕德，一份烤，一份炸
Two bhakri, two papad, one roasted, one fried.
还有... 洋葱番茄沙拉
And... an onion-tomato salad.
- 还有...-raita
- And... - Raita.
还有 raita
And raita.
取消掉
Cancel it.
我吃饱了
I'm full.
好吧，取消订单
Okay, cancel the order.
呃... 刚才有点着急... 我忘了点酸辣酱..
Uh... in the hurry... I forgot raita...
那么，我该拿你怎么办呢？
So, what should we do?
雇我吧，我会像您儿子一样
Hire me, I'm like your son.
明天上午9点，布尚会带你去交易所
Tomorrow 9 am. Bhushan will take you to the ring.
-布尚是谁?-我们以前的股票经纪人
- Who's Bhushan? - Our old jobber.
他对市场了如指掌
He knows the market very well.
让我们拭目以待，明天命运之门会不会为你敞开
Let's see, if the door to your destiny opens in the market tomorrow.
- 黑眼镜蛇-嗯？
- Black Cobra. - Huh?
你正盯着看的那个
The one you're staring at.
他的名字是马努·蒙德拉
His name is Manu Mundra.
但在市场上，他被称为黑眼镜蛇
But in the market, he's known as Black Cobra.
他是市场上最大的悲观主义者
He's the biggest pessimist in the market.
悲观主义者？
Pessimist?
当市场上涨时，他会把它拉回来
When the market is moving up, he pulls it back down.
跌得越低，马努·蒙德拉的利润就越高
The lower the market falls, the higher Manu Mundra's profits.
- 所以他是熊-是的，他是熊
- So, he's a Bear. - Yes, he's a Bear.
- 你是?-布尚·巴特
- And you are? - Bhushan Bhatt.
- 哈尔沙德 · 梅塔 -我知道
- Harshad Mehta. - I know, Harshad Shantilal Mehta.
安巴拉 · 萨希卜派我来的
Ambalal Saheb has sent me.
我是他以前的股票经纪人，来，穿上这个
I'm his old jobber. Here, wear this.
从现在开始，这就是你在市场上的身份，好吗？
From now on, this will be your identity in the market. Okay?
来吧
Come on.
[汽车鸣笛]
[car honks]
把车停在后面的停车场，小心点
Park it in the back lot. Be careful.
普拉纳夫 · 谢斯！
Pranav Sheth!
你要在这里杀了我们吗，就像在市场上那样？
You will kill us here like you do in the market?
亲爱的布尚，如果你挡我的路，我会碾死你！
If you come in my way, I will have to run you over, Bhushan darling!
- 普拉纳夫兄弟，你有什么建议吗?-我们这儿有个菜鸟
Pranav Bhai, got any tips? We have a rookie here.
你好
Hello.
即使是我自己的父亲，我也不免费给情报
I don't give tips for free even to my own father.
明白了吗? 傻冒！
Get it? Silly jobber!
他也是独一无二的
He's also one of a kind. Pranav Sheth.
他在短时间内完成了重要的交易
He has played a big game in a short period of time.
他是个乐观主义者
He is an optimist.
他是推动市场上涨的人之一
He is one of those who push the market upwards.
- 你是说，他是头公牛-是的，公牛
- You mean, he's a Bull. - Yes, Bull.
你知道为什么这些悲观主义者和乐观主义者被称为熊市和牛市吗？
Do you know why these pessimists and optimists are called Bears and Bulls?
告诉我？
Tell me?
熊总是把猎物往下打
A bear always hits it's prey downwards.
公牛总是用它的角把猎物往上抛
And a bull always tosses its prey upwards with its horns.
看来你还做了些准备，是吗? 很好
Seems you've read some English books. Homework, is it? Good.
但请记住，这不是美国的华尔街
But remember. This is not America's Wall Street.
这里是孟买的达拉尔街
This is Bombay's Dalal Street.
这里，是一个赌场
And this here, is a betting ground.
无论熊是向下击打你，还是公牛向上抛掷你，这都无关紧要
It doesn't matter if the bear hits you downwards or the bull tosses you upwards.
不管怎样，你都会被击倒
Either way, you will be knocked out.
所以，不要太聪明，好吗? 我们走
So, don't be over smart. Okay? Let's go.
[ 布尚 ]‘你会记住这些手势的，对吗? ’
[Bhushan] 'You will remember the signs, right?'
这意味着客户想要卖出，这意味着他想要购买
This means the customer wants to sell and this means he wants to buy.
用手指传递数量和价格，好吗？
Use your fingers to convey the quantity and the price. Okay?
你还记得我教你什么吗? 25，50，12,12.5..
Do you remember what I taught you? 25 paise, 50 paise, 12, 12.5...
... 27.5,5,500也可能是5,000
...27.5, 5, 500. It could also be 5,000.
- 记住... 听着!-嗯？
- And remember... Listen! - Huh?
如果你有什么不明白的，就问我
If you don't understand something, ask me.
如果你不问，你就学不到东西
If you don't ask, you won't learn.
第一天上班别以为自己是专家
Don't think you're an expert on your first day.
好吗? 过来
Okay? Come.
- 这是25 -不... 我要去厕所
- That's 25. - No... I've to go to the toilet.
你能坚持两个小时! 我们走！
You can hold it for two hours! Let's go!
如果你看到一个拥挤的地方，就认为那是我们的地盘
If you see a crowded spot, consider that's our area.
那就是你要呆的地方
And that's where you will stay.
而如果有的地方只有一小群人，假定是一个贫民窟..
And the area with a small crowd, assume that a slum...
... 只有先令和便士... 我们不在那里做生意
...only shillings and pennies... we don't do business there.
为什么？
Why?
因为那是廉价股票经纪人的工作范围
Because that's where the penny stock jobbers operate.
小股票以低价出售
Small shares sold at cheap prices.
永远远离零钱
Always stay away from small change.
因为我们只经营高价值的股票
Because we deal only in high-value stocks.
这是一个数百万的游戏
It's a game of millions.
所以，眼观六路，耳听八方
So keep your eyes, ears and mind wide open.
好吧，告诉我，我们国家的运动是什么？
Okay, tell me something. What's our national sport?
- 板球-嘿! 是曲棍球
- Cricket. - Hey! It's hockey.
哦，是的，曲棍球
Oh yes, hockey.
这就像曲棍球
This is just like hockey.
铃声一响，经纪人的游戏就开始了
At the sound of the bell, starts the jobber's hell.
最后一次铃响的时候... 游戏结束了
And at the last bell, well... game over.
在这个过程中，进球最多的人获胜
During this, the one who strikes the most goals, wins.
[ 布尚 ]‘集中精神，我的冠军’
[Bhushan] 'So concentrate, my champion.'
[人群尖叫]
[crowd screaming]
嘿! 你在笑什么？
Hey! What are you grinning at?
这不是电影！
This is not a movie!
如果你不做交易
If you don't strike deals...
这将是你的最后一天！
...your first day will be your last!
快点，开始工作！
Come on, get to work!
550... 500...
[广播]
[loudspeaker announcement]
[安巴拉尔]“多么完美的开始啊! ”
[Ambalal] 'What an auspicious beginning!'
开始就做得一团糟! Vaandha! 你明白吗？
You've started with a mess! Vaandha! Do you understand?
告诉他Vaandha是什么意思
Tell him what vaandha means.
这意味着... 你卖出了价值2.5万的股票
That means... you've sold stocks worth 25,000.
但交易员说，他只买了价值2.3万的股票
But the dealer says he has only bought stocks worth 23,000.
- 所以这2000的差额...-... 是损失！
- So this difference of 2,000... - ...That's a loss!
你明白什么是损失吗? 谁来赔偿？
Do you understand loss? Who will cover it?
老板，我告诉过他要眼观六路，耳听八方
Saheb, I had told him to keep his eyes, ears, and mind wide open.
老板... 那里那么拥挤，那么吵..
See... It was so crowded, so noisy...
交易所里吗看起来像个鱼市
The ring felt like a fish market.
事情发生得太快了，我一定是搞错了
Things were happening so fast. I must have made a mistake.
是的，你搞砸了
You're right. You have made a mistake.
如果你连算数都算不好... ... 趁早别干了
If you can't even calculate... leave the ring.
我承认我犯了个错误
Look, I agree I've made a mistake.
至于损失，您可以从我的工资里扣除
And as far as the loss goes, you can deduct that from my salary.
“从我的薪水里扣除” ，他说！
"Deduct from my salary", he says!
让他明白... ... 没有利润就没有薪水
Make him understand... ...no profit means no salary.
我一定会赚钱的，再给我一次机会
I will surely make profit. Give me one more chance.
给你一个机会就意味着要冒险，我承担不起
Giving you a chance means taking a risk, which I can't afford.
不冒险，就是市场上最大的风险
Not taking risks, is the biggest risk in the market.
市场在一天之内就教会了我这一点
If nothing, the market has taught me this in one day.
你觉得..
Do you think…
安巴拉尔给了你另一次机会是帮了你一个忙？
…Ambalal saheb has done you a favour by giving you another chance?
我认识他很多年了，他是个游戏高手
I've known him for years. He's a master of his game.
记住一件事，如果这不能达到他的目的，他甚至会放弃上帝
Remember one thing. If it doesn't serve his purpose, he will even give up on God.
你损失的2000卢比对他来说根本不算损失
Your 2,000 rupee loss makes no difference to him.
你第一天就卖出了价值2.5万的股票
You've sold stocks worth 25,000 on your very first day.
你以为他会轻易放你走吗？
Do you think he'd let you go so easily? Huh?
你只需要集中注意力，一个接一个地达到目标，就是这样
You just have to focus and hit goal after goal. That's it.
别担心，喝点茶吧
[Bhushan] 'Don't worry. Have some tea.'
[苏切塔]“哈尔沙德现在只想着一件事”
[Sucheta] 'Harshad had only one thing on his mind now.'
孟买交易所
'The BSE ring'.
一旦他回到交易所..
'And once he got back into the ring...'
不到一年，他就成了业内最好的经纪人之一
'...within a year, he became one of the best jobbers in the business.'
不好意思! 嘿! 听着
Excuse me! Hey! Listen.
- 卓越汽车多少钱?-32.5-35
- How much for Premier Auto? - 32.5-35.
有效数量是多少？
For what quantity is it valid?
- 五百-好吧，给我五百
- Five hundred. - Fine, give me 500.
35每股，一共500股
Five hundred for 35.
你能再卖给我500股吗？
Can you give me 500 more for the same value?
- 35-37.5-好吧给我500
- 35-37.5. - Okay, fine. Give me 500.
再买1000股多少钱？
How much for another 1,000 shares?
- 37.5-40.-太贵了！
- 37.5-40. - That's quite high!
- 好吧，我买1000-拿去吧
- Okay, I'll buy 1,000. - Take it.
- 能再给我1000股吗? -我没有了
- Can you give me 1,000 more? - I'm done.
来吧，勇敢点! 再卖给我一些
Come on, be brave! Sell me some more.
我没有股份了! 去找大公司吧
I'm out of shares! Go to the bigger guys.
都卖光了... 嘿..
They're all out... Hey...
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
卓越汽车将提高汽车价格不久
PREMIERE AUTO WILL INCREASE CAR PRICES SHORTLY
我现在明白为什么卓越汽车的股票..
I understand now why shares of Premier Auto...
过去几天一直畅销不衰
...have been selling like hotcakes for the last few days.
看看这个
Look at this.
卓越公司正在提高汽车价格
Premier is hiking the prices of its cars.
一定是有人泄露了这个消息
Someone must've leaked this information.
只有掌握这些信息的人才能赚大钱
It's the people with such information who make tons of money.
这叫做内幕交易
This is called insider trading.
在印度以外的地方，是要严格处理的
It's dealt with strictly, outside India.
等着瞧吧
Just wait and watch.
卓越汽车今天的需求量将会很大
Premier Auto will be in high demand today.
如果价格上涨，我们将会遭受巨大的损失
If the price surges, we'll incur a huge loss.
不能再这样下去了
We can't work like this.
我们也要收集这样的内部信息
We must gather such insider information too.
你疯了吗？
Have you lost your mind?
这是有钱人的游戏，我们不能玩
This is a rich man's game. We can't play it.
别再说游戏了！
Don't start with games again!
你不断地把市场变成一场曲棍球比赛... 一个摔跤场... 一个拳击场..
You keep turning the market into a game of hockey... a wrestling pit... a boxing ring...
这就是我们的问题，我们从来不玩真正的游戏
And that's our problem. We never play the real game.
我们只看有钱人玩耍，并为他们欢呼
We only watch the rich at play, and cheer for them.
- 我们为什么不去一起玩呢?-啊？
- Why don't we enter the playground? - Huh?
[哈沙德]‘即使是第12个人，这次我们也要入场'
[Harshad] 'Even if as the 12th man, let's enter the playground this time.'
我们在员工之间建立小范围的联系... ..
'Let's make contacts at a small level, among the employees...'
像工人，守望者，苦工，工会工人..
'...like workers, watchmen, peons, union workers...'
如果我们努力寻找，我相信我们会找到了解公司决策细节的人
'If we look hard, I'm sure we'll find someone who knows the details of the company's decisions.'
“满足我们的要求... ... ”
[Factory Workers] 'Fulfil our demands...'
满足我们的要求... ..
'Fulfil our demands...'
这次抗议是为了什么，兄弟？
What's this protest about, brother?
还是老样子..
Same as always...
满足我们的要求... ..
'Fulfil our demands...'
继续
Keep going.
这位萨希卜医生是谁？
Who's this doctor saheb?
邦主医生，我是达达 · 萨塔姆医生
Doctor saheb, is Dr. Dada Satam.
他的职业是医生，但他也是所有这些工会的领导人
He's a doctor by profession but he's also the leader of all these unions.
所有的最终决定都由他做出
All final decisions are taken by him.
你好，找我有什么事？
Yes, tell me. What's the problem?
医生您好，我该怎么说呢？
[in Marathi] Doctor, what can I say?
[马拉地语]我想要很多麻烦
[in Marathi] I want lots of trouble.
不要说错马拉地语我很懂印地语
Don't speak in wrong Marathi. I know Hindi very well.
- 直说吧-那太好了
- Tell me. - Oh, then I don't have any problem.
市场有问题，市场真的很有问题
The market has a problem. The market is really in a problem.
人们每天都在不停地尖叫
All day, people screaming nonstop.
有时价格上涨，有时价格下跌
Sometimes the price is up, sometimes it's down.
有时候我觉得我的头会像足球一样爆炸
Sometimes I feel my head will explode like a football.
当然，也有令人心碎的地方
And of course, there's the heartbreak too.
你是来打发时间的吗？
Are you here to pass time?
不，不是那样的，邦主医生
No, it isn't that, doctor saheb.
我是哈尔沙德 · 梅塔，我在证券交易所工作
I'm Harshad Mehta. I work in the share market.
那又怎样？
So?
所以... 事情是这样的，股票市场和工会工人之间……
So... the thing is, the relationship between the share market...
就像婆媳关系
...and union workers is like a woman's relationship with her mother-in-law.
您看... 如果媳妇做了什么好事..
Look... if the daughter-in-law does something good...
她的婆婆很高兴，价格也上涨了
...her mother-in-law is happy. The value goes up.
如果她不做家务了，婆婆就会生气，媳妇的价值就会下降
If she stops doing chores, mother-in-law gets angry and the value goes down.
- 如果她玩什么新花样...-起来
- And if she does something new... - Get up.
- 什么?-起来滚开
- What? - Get up and get lost.
- 出去!-医生..
- Get out! - Doctor...
你的心碎让我头疼，出去
Your heartbreak is giving me a headache. Get out.
- 下一个进来，快-等一下
- Hey, send in the next. Go. - Wait a minute.
医生，听我说
Doctor, listen to me.
我想说的是，公司的产量上升时
What I'm trying to say is, the share price of the company increases...
- 股价就会上涨-是的，那又怎样？
- ...when the production increases. - Yes, so?
所以，是这样的... 卓越汽车公司已经提高了今天的汽车价格
So, the thing is Doctor... Premier has raised the price of its cars today.
但在过去的七天里，其股票的价格和需求一直在上升
But the price and demand for its shares has been increasing over the last seven days.
为什么? 你觉得呢？
Why? What do you think?
谁是幕后黑手? 你觉得这对谁有好处？
Who was behind this? And who do you think benefitted?
这对工人有帮助吗? 对你有好处吗？
Did it help the worker? Did it benefit you?
想想吧，没人受益
Just think. Nobody benefitted.
我来这里只是为了讨论工人的利益
I'm here to only discuss benefit for the workers.
我只是想知道工厂里发生了什么事
I just want to know what's going on in the factory.
我是说日常生产的细节
I mean, daily production details.
关于增加产量的细节... 还有罢工的细节... 就是这些
Details regarding the increase in production... impending strikes... that's it.
你看，市场可以对这些内幕信息做出反应
Look, the market can be made to react with this insider information.
我会给你们一部分我从中获得的利润
And I'll give you a part of the profit that I make from this.
我的意思是，这是给你的工人们的，这笔钱将会是他们的基金
I mean, it's for your labourers. It'll go towards their fund.
[阿什温]“你知道达达萨坦是什么样的人吗? ”
[Ashwin] 'Do you know what sort of man this Dada Satam is?'
我认为他不会同意你的提议
I don't think he'll agree to what you've proposed.
当他想明白的时候，我的电话就会响
When it strikes his mind, my phone will ring.
我给了他我的电话号码
I've given him my number.
听着，任何事情都有代价，我们也必须付出代价
Look, everything has a price and we have to pay this price.
嘿，给我切碎的沙拉
Hey, give me chopped salad.
听我说... 你为什么要从事内幕交易？
Listen to me... why are you getting into insider trading?
如果出了什么差错..
If anything goes wrong...
然后像安巴拉和达达萨塔姆这样的人会把你切成沙拉
...then people like Ambalal and Dada Satam will chop you into a salad.
问题和技巧，糖果和零食..
Problems and hacks, sweets and snacks...
没人能把这些从古吉拉特人手里抢走
...nobody can take these away from a Gujarati.
你擅长沟通，但是有风险
You are good at dialogues. But it's risky.
风险是生活的调味品
Risk is the spice of life.
- [ Sucheta ]“当哈尔沙德从任何公司得到内部消息的时候 ”-喂？
- [Sucheta] 'Whenever Harshad got inside information from any company...' - Hello?
他就会瞄准他们的股票
'...he would target their stocks.'
第一汽车多少钱？
How much for Premier Auto?
37.5-40.
他出价36-38.5
He's giving it for 36-38.5.
- 那就去跟他买啊!-滚开
- Then go and buy it from him! - Get lost.
如果消息是负面的，他会以低价出售这些股票
[Sucheta] 'If the information was negative, he would offer those stocks at a low price.'
消息一出来，股价就会进一步下跌
'The moment the news would come out, the stock prices would drop further.'
哈尔沙德会把它们买回来
'And Harshad would buy them back.'
“同样，如果他得到了积极的信息... ... ”
'Similarly, if he received positive information...'
’ ... 他就开始囤积那些公司的股票... ’
'...he would corner those stocks...'
’ ... 当消息一出来，股票价格就会飙升... ’
'...when the news would come out, the stock prices would surge...'
“哈尔沙德在把它们卖掉”
'...and Harshad would sell them.'
他们罢工了，价格下降了
They're on strike, the price has dropped.
请从我这里买1000股
Buy 1000 shares from me, please.
成交
Done.
[ Sucheta ]“不管公司赚不赚钱... ... ”
[Sucheta] 'Irrespective of gain or loss for the company...'
“哈萨德是在赚钱的”
'Harshad was minting profits.'
有时候是熊，大多数时候是牛
'Sometimes as a Bear, and mostly as a Bull.'
他开始与多家公司进行这种内幕交易
'He began to do this kind of insider trading with various companies.'
“ Shree 合成纤维，国家人造丝，大东方航运... ... ”
'Shree Synthetics, National Rayon, Great Eastern Shipping...'
“ ... 名单还很长”
'...and the list went on.'
哈尔沙德的利润一直在增长
'And Harshad's profits kept growing.'
哈沙德，我想这个周末去我的村子看看
Harshad, I'm thinking of visiting my village this weekend.
这次我们赚了不少钱
We've made a lot of profit this time.
这不是利润，这叫佣金
This is not profit, it's called commission.
- 利润归杜拉拉-杜拉拉？
- Profit goes to the Lala. - Lala?
- 你的老板-哦，安巴拉 · 萨希卜
- Your boss. - Oh, Ambalal Saheb.
现在，名字，客户和利润，都将是我的
Now, the name, the clients and profit, all will be mine.
是时候开立我自己的交易账户了
It's time to open my own trading account.
那这份工作呢？
And what about this job?
你以为我是来干活的吗？
Do you think I was here to do a job?
我是来学习的
I was here to learn.
我已经学得够多了
I've learnt enough.
我已经和苏雷什 · 巴海谈过了
I've already spoken to Suresh Bhai.
苏雷什 · 南德拉尔 · 沙赫
Suresh Nandlal Shah.
我的交易账户再过几天就要开户了
My trading account will be open in a few days.
- 你看到了吗?-什么？
-[Harshad] 'Did you see that?' - What?
Patan的上等布料
Special fabric from Patan.
兄弟的妻子送来的
Bhushan bhai's wife has sent it.
怎么回事，梅塔先生? 你今天看起来很高兴
What's up, Mr. Mehta? You seem very happy today.
我辞职了
I've quit my job.
那你还高兴? ！
And you're happy about it?!
- 我要开始我自己的事业了-什么意思？
- I'm starting something of my own. - What does that mean?
这意味着我们会飞黄腾达
That means we're going to prosper.
我不再是一个证券经纪人了，我已经开了自己的交易账户
I'm not a jobber anymore. I've opened my own trading account.
我明白，但这有什么区别呢？
I get that. But what's the difference?
现在很不一样了，赚来的所有钱都是我们的
It's very different. Now all the money will be ours.
你在说什么? 把一切都告诉我
What are you saying? Tell me everything.
一个妻子必须知道她丈夫做什么
A wife must know what her husband does.
你是说你想告诉你父母？
You mean you want to tell your parents?
告诉他们，哈尔沙德就要走向人生巅峰了
Tell them Harshad's family is going to prosper.
好吧，别告诉我了
Okay, don't tell me.
那么，如果我告诉你，你会理解吗？
So, if I tell you, will you understand?
你可以试着让我理解
You can at least try.
来吧
Come.
过来坐下
Come here. Sit.
你看，经纪人的工作就像一列慢车
Look. A jobber's work is like a slow train.
- 慢车每站都停对吧?-是的
- A slow train stops at every station, right? - Yes.
红灯停，绿灯行
Starts at the green signal and stops at the red signal.
就是这样..
Exactly like that...
经纪人只是服从命令
...a jobber just follows orders.
经纪人说买，你就买，经纪人说卖，你就卖
The broker says buy, and you buy. The broker says sell, and you sell.
在这场闹剧之后，我们得到了什么？
And what do we get after performing in this circus?
只不过是一个打工人
Nothing but a vaandha.
老板赚取了所有的利润
The boss and the broker make all the profit.
当我们拥有自己的交易账户时，我们的生活会发生怎样的变化
When we have our own trading account watch how our life changes.
慢车将转入古吉拉特快车
The slow train will turn into The Gujarat Express.
我们将用自己的钱投资
We will invest our own money.
我们将在市场上占有一席之地，摆脱老板的束缚
We will take a position in the market, then we will square it off ourselves.
- 你明白了吗?-当然
- Did you understand? - Of course.
一点点
A little bit.
但是如果你能充满爱意地解释这一点，我会更好地理解它
But if you had explained this lovingly I would have understood it better.
这样的爱足够吗？
Is this much love enough?
- 这是从哪来的?-从这个决定来的
- Where did this come from? - It came from this decision.
很美，不是吗？
It's beautiful, isn't it?
谁会庆祝辞职？
Who celebrates on quitting a job?
我不明白
I don't understand it.
爸爸，菜单上有什么你看不懂的？
Pappa, what don't you understand in the menu?
不是菜单，我是搞不懂你
Not the menu. I don't understand you.
真的吗? 我这么单纯！
Really? I'm so simple!
你在说什么？
What are you saying?
别理他，你来点菜
Ignore him. You place the order.
- 这里...-我不明白的是..
- Here... - What I don't understand is...
你辞掉了一份高薪的工作，还在这里浪费钱？
...you have quit a well-paying job, and you're wasting money here?
你中彩票了吗？
Have you won a lottery?
爸爸，这比中彩票还重要
Pappa, this is bigger than a lottery.
我们已经开了自己的交易账户
We've opened our own trading account.
- 你说”我们”是什么意思?-我们，哈沙德和我
- What do you mean "we"? - We. Harshad and I.
我也决定在结婚前辞掉工作
Even I've decided to quit my job before marriage.
怎么回事? 买肥皂吗? 还买一送一！
What is happening? Are we buying soap? Buy one, get one free!
你们都辞职了却没人告诉我? ！
You've both quit your jobs and nobody's told me?!
谁能解释一下这个家里发生了什么？
Can someone explain what's happening in this family?
你想知道什么？
What do you want to know?
我们努力工作，填满的却是别人的口袋
We use our brains to fill other pockets.
还要这样做多久？
How long will we keep doing this?
如果我们动动脑子努力工作
If we are working hard and applying our brains...
就应该得到利润，不是吗？
...we should be the ones getting the profit, right?
孩子，如果利润是你的，损失也是你的
Son, if the profit is yours, the loss will be yours too.
问我吧，我有经验
Ask me, I have the experience.
即使是纺织品市场也有风险
Even the textile market can't be trusted...
他说的是股票市场
...and he is talking about the share market.
给他点些甜点
Order something sweet for him...
让他说点好听的
...so that he utters something sweet.
说这么尖酸刻薄的话！
Such bitter words!
他们在做好事，如果你不能祝他们好运
They're on to something good. If you can't wish them luck then...
祝好不会带来利润
Wishing luck doesn't bring profit in a business.
如果我说这家餐厅不错，我可以免费在这吃吗？
If I say this restaurant is good, will I get free food?
嘿... 服务员，打扰一下
Hey... Waiter. Excuse me, please.
你的餐厅是最好的，非常好，第一名
Your restaurant is the best. Very good. Number one.
既然我已经对你的餐厅赞不绝口了，我能在这里免费吃饭吗？
Now that I've praised your restaurant so much, will I get to eat here for free?
兄弟，来，我们回家吧
Bhai, come, let's go home.
- 不...-我们回家吃晚饭吧-别理他..
- No... - Let's have dinner at home. - Ignore him...
- 他破坏了气氛-没错！
- He's ruined the mood. - That's correct!
把钱存起来，你会需要的
Save the money, you will need it.
你在说什么? 快点菜吧
What are you saying? Place the order.
- 先生，您要点什么?-当然，点吧
- Sir, can I take your order? - Sure, take it.
一盘智慧，一盘聪明..
A plate of wisdom, a plate of smartness...
还有一些责任
...and some responsibility.
- 你们有这个吗?-菜单上没有
- Do you serve those? - That's not on the menu.
那就听她的，她有的是智慧、聪明和责任
Then take it from her. She has plenty.
- 是的-等一下..
- Yes, I do. - Wait a minute...
- 过来-好的拿着这个
- Come here. - Yes. Here, take this.
- 5个...-给我一个吉什蒂
- 5 rotis... - One khichdi for me.
“好的，给他来点热乎乎的吉什蒂”
[Harshad] 'Yes, get some hot khichdi for him.'
我知道你会是第一个离开这里的人，我是对的，不是吗？
I knew you'd be the first one to leave this place. I was right, wasn't I?
谁知道阿什温真的会结婚？
Who knew Ashwin would really get married?
现在这房子太小了
This house is too small now.
我在坎迪瓦里找到了一栋大房子，价格是15万卢比
We've found a big house in Kandivali for one and a half lakh rupees.
我们买下了它，为了未来着想
We've bought it, keeping the future in mind.
你总是想着未来
You always think about the future.
那么，以后不再玩板球和丹迪亚了？
So, no more cricket and Dandiya?
嘿! 我只是在换房子，有不是换朋友
Hey! I'm just changing homes not friends.
我会回来和你玩丹迪亚的游戏，然后把你打得稀巴烂
I'll come back to play Dandiya and bowl you a googly.
你有时间吗？
Will you have the time?
如果你有时间，来我这里了解一下股票市场
If you have time, come to my place to learn about the share market.
又来了，我不懂股票
There you go again. I don't understand shares.
为什么不呢? 你是第一个犹豫投资的古吉拉特人
Why not? You're the first Gujarati who hesitates to invest.
任何事都有风险
Everything is risky.
一旦你学会了，你可以在一个月内赚到你现在的年收入
Once you learn, you can earn your annual income in a month.
- 不可能-有可能
- That's not possible. - It is possible.
有空回家吧
Come home sometime.
- 我会带你到处看看，教你股票市场的知识-再见! 再见
- I'll show you around and teach you about the share market. - See you! Bye-bye.
- 再见-来吧我们走
- Bye. - Come on, let's go.
来吧
Come on.
- 喝茶-给他来点
- Tea. - Give him some.
他刚结婚，至少要宠他一年
He's newly married. Pamper him for a year at least.
嫂子，去休息吧，你们还在蜜月期
Bhabhi, go, take rest. This is your honeymoon period.
聪明过头先生! 管好你自己的事
Mr. Oversmart! Mind your own business.
你们去忙吧
You both go on please.
安华制药公司? 这是哪家公司？
Anwar Pharma? Which company is this?
是阿瓦尔制药公司
It's Alwar Pharma.
- 嫂子，快给他配眼镜吧! -你为什么要投资这家公司？
- Bhabhi, get him spectacles! - Why are you investing in this company?
你收到消息了吗？
Did you get a tip?
不，但是我们要创造一个消息，并且在市场上传播这个消息
No, but we have to create a tip and spread that tip across the market.
兄弟，这只股票值多少钱？
Bhai, this is like peanuts. What tip is this stock worth?
- 股价只有5卢比-没错
- The share price is only five rupees. - Exactly.
只要5卢比，如果我们批量购买，价值会自动增加
Only five rupees. If we buy it in bulk, the value will increase automatically.
如果我们散布谣言，那些饥肠辘辘的商人就会表现得像一群羊
And if we spread a rumour about it, the hungry dealers will act like a flock of sheep.
在适当的时候，我们会抛售股票，获得可观的利润
At the right time, we'll dump the shares and book a healthy profit.
这听起来很简单，但却不切实际
It sounds easy but it's not practical.
我知道
I know.
我们的钱只够买两万股
Look, we have enough money to buy only 20,000 shares.
- 是的-如果我们有钱再买两万..
- Yes. - If we get money to buy another 20,000...
这将是我们的第一桶金！
...it'll be a feast for us!
再来两万? 谁给我们钱？
Money for 20,000 more? Who will give us the money?
市场上没有人像你这样的疯子
Nobody in the market has lost their mind like you.
-安华制药公司-是阿瓦尔制药公司！
- Anwar Pharma. - It's Alwar Pharma!
普拉纳夫 · 巴伊
Pranav Bhai.
我是哈尔沙德·梅塔，我是个股票经纪人
I'm Harshad Mehta. I'm a broker.
- 那又怎样?-我想跟你谈谈，就五分钟
- So? - I need to talk to you. Just 5 minutes.
现在不行，我没心情
Not now. I'm not in the mood.
不管怎样，我什么都闻不到
Anyway, I can't smell anything.
你好，普拉那夫 · 巴伊
Hello, Pranav Bhai.
- 这里禁止吸烟-我是哈沙德，我们昨天见过面吗？
- Smoking is not allowed here. - I'm Harshad. We met yesterday?
- 那又怎样?-我们能谈五分钟吗？
- Yeah, so? - Can we talk for five minutes?
看你能不能嗅到什么商机
See, if you can smell something.
你要的五分钟，我马上给你答案
You asked for five minutes, I'll answer in a second.
不感兴趣
Not interested.
-听我说-你能告诉我什么？
- Pranav Bhai, listen to me. - What can you tell me? Huh?
我能闻到钞票的味道，钞票吸引钞票，硬币吸引硬币
I can smell cash. Notes attracts notes. And pennies attract pennies.
你是认为我的客户太小了，他们都用硬币来交易吗？
Do you think my clients are so small that they'll deal in pennies?
告诉我，普拉那夫 · 巴伊
Tell me something, Pranav Bhai.
在印度，哪种钞票被造假最多？
Which is the most counterfeited currency denomination in India?
- 100卢比的纸币-不，不是纸币，是硬币
- The 100 rupee note. - No. Not the notes, it's the coins.
25，50面值的硬币
25 paise, 50 paise, one rupee coins.
每个人都专注于纸币，没有人看硬币
Everyone focuses on the notes, no one looks at the coins.
同样，没有人会关注低价股
Similarly, nobody looks at the penny stocks.
它们很容易操作
They're very easy to operate.
如果我们运作得当，利润是有保障的
And if we operate them properly, profit is guaranteed.
操作? 你想操纵股价？
Operate? You want to operate stocks?
这是违法的，你会进监狱的，明白吗？
Operating stocks is illegal. You will end up in jail, get it?
兄弟，就像你可以闻到钞票的味道
Pranav Bhai, just like you can smell currency notes...
我从这些叮当响的硬币中听到了财富的声音
...I hear the sound of wealth in these jingling pennies.
试一试吧
Just give it a try.
尝试？
Try?
这样吧
Do one thing.
把这些都拿去你自己试吧
Take all of this and try it yourself.
我不要钱，你留着吧
I don't want money. Keep this.
让我们一起做吧
Let's do it together.
该死
Bloody hell!
五分钟后，你就会说“让我们一起做吧” ! ？
In five minutes, you've gotten to "Let's do it together"!?
你想做什么？
What do you want to do?
今天来交易所，你会看到阿尔瓦制药公司出现在董事会上
Come to the ring today. You'll see Alwar Pharma on the board.
阿瓦尔制药公司？
Alwar Pharma?
哈尔沙德有一些内部消息
Harshad Bhai has some inside information.
让我们看看今天会发生什么
Let's see what happens today.
如果哈尔沙德说的是真的，那么这一定是真的
If Harshad Bhai is saying then it must be definitely true.
- 给我也买一些 -好的
- Then buy some for me too. - Okay.
听着，哈尔沙德有内幕消息，阿尔瓦制药公司将会..
Listen, Harshad Bhai has a tip. Alwar Pharma is going to surge...
即使超过25% 或30% 也没关系，明白吗？
It's fine even if it crosses the limit by 25 or 30 per cent, get it?
快点，走，快！
Come on, go. Quick!
兄弟，你确定这样行得通吗？
Bhai, you're sure this will work, right?
- 不会出问题吧?-别担心，不会出问题的
- Nothing will go wrong? - Don't worry. Nothing will go wrong.
你怎么能确定不会出问题？
How are you so sure it won't go wrong?
这是我们第一次这样做
This is the first time we're doing this.
这不会是最后一次，相信我，来吧
It won't be the last time, trust me. Come.
“亚洲电报36.15,39.20”
[Man1] 'Asian Cables 36.15, 39.20.'
Ceat 107.68,110.22
'Ceat 107.68, 110.22'
克朗普顿 · 格里夫斯91.38,94.24’
'Crompton Greaves 91.38, 94.24'
塔塔钢铁234.12,237.23
'Tata Steel 234.12, 237.23.'
阿尔瓦制药 17.20,20
'Alwar Pharma 17.20, 20.'
你知道谁总是赢吗？
Do you know who always wins?
最快的那个
The fastest one.
历史见证了猎豹永远是赢家
History is witness. The cheetah always wins.
每个人都出价买这匹马
Everyone bids on the horse.
但是马只会跑，猎豹是最快的
But the horse only runs. Cheetah is the fastest.
你是今天交易所的印度豹
You were the cheetah in the ring today.
我这里还有两只股票
I have two more stocks in mind.
Blowcast和印度齿轮
Blowcast... and India Gears.
我们五五分成怎么样？
Shall we go 50-50?
成交
Done.
这是不可能的，没有公司会倒闭
That's not possible. No company will shut down.
“哟，哈尔沙德! ”
[Man2] 'Oh, Harshad!'
“兄弟! ”
'Harshad Bhai!'
哈尔沙德
Harshad Bhai.
等等，你买了辆新车! 太好了！
Wait. You've bought a new car! Great!
- 今天的茶钱是你付的-是的
- You're paying for our tea today. - Yes.
我每天都给你们付茶钱
I pay for your tea every day.
别管茶了，告诉我今天买什么？
Forget tea. Tell me what to buy today?
买塔塔的股
Buy any Tata share.
别想太多，这是一家老公司
Don't think so much. It's an old company.
它迟早会给你带来利润
Sooner or later, it is sure to give you a profit.
你投资新公司，买车... ..
You're investing in new companies and buying cars...
- 然后让我们投资老公司? -就是啊
- ...and telling us to invest in old ones? - That's true, Harshad Bhai.
好吧，那就投我刚投的那家新公司吧
Fine, invest in the new ones like me.
- 但是如果跌了，那是你的责任，好吗?-不，这不公平
- But if you face a loss, it's on you. Okay? - No! That's not fair.
兄弟，在巨额利润的背后，同样有巨大的风险
Brother, behind a large profit, is also a large risk.
如果你和我一样，也喜欢冒险，那就冒险一试吧
If like me, you too love taking risks, then take the plunge.
你要么死，要么暴富
You'll die or you'll fly.
这就是新公司的运作方式
That's how new companies work.
- ‘市场崩溃了... ’-一旦崩溃..
- 'The market has crashed...' - Once it falls...
市场崩溃了... ..
'The market has crashed...'
[人群尖叫]
[crowd screaming]
哈尔沙德，我们损失了一百万卢比！
Harshad, we've lost 10 lakhs!
有人在半小时内改变了游戏规则
Someone changed the game in just half an hour.
有人在市场上抛售了35万股 Reliance 股票
Someone has dumped 3.5 lakh Reliance shares in the market.
谁干的? 是 Manu Bhai 吗？
Who did this? Is it Manu Bhai?
还有Telco和太钢也有大量抛售
There is also heavy selling in Telco and Tisco.
这是百分之八到百分之十的暴跌，兄弟
It's an eight to ten percent crash, Bhai.
人们说是加尔各答熊做的
People are saying that Calcutta Bears have done this.
- 一个叫 Ajay Makadia 的人...-Ajay Kedia！
- Someone named Ajay Makadia... - Ajay Kedia!
不管他是谁，我们完了，兄弟！
Whoever the hell he is, we're finished, Bhai!
一切都结束了
Everything's over.
100万卢比啊，兄弟
Ten lakh rupees, Bhai.
[苏切塔]“那一天，似乎哈尔沙德的罪恶结束了”
[Sucheta] 'That day, it seemed as if Harshad's inning is over.'
但是游戏还没有开始
'But the game had not even begun yet.'
他的故事还有十年才结束
'The end of his story, was still a decade away.'
- 喂?-喂，我是苏切塔
-[DT] 'Hello?' -[Sucheta] 'Yeah, Sucheta here.'
听着，我们现在非常需要赶上进度
'Listen we need to catch up very urgently.'
线人就在我面前... ..
'The source is right in front of me...'
“他告诉我，哈尔萨德可能与 SBI 有个巨大的骗局”
'...and he's telling me that Harshad might be in serious trouble with SBI.'
我只需要你给我解释一些技术细节，我们能见个面吗
'I just need you to explain a few technicalities to me, can we meet?'
- 好的，没问题-谢谢，再见
-[DT] 'Yeah, sure.' -[Sucheta] 'Thank you, I'll see you.'
坐在这里的那个人去哪了？
Where is the man who was sitting here?
我给他端了一杯茶，我不知道他去哪了
I brought tea for him. I don't know where he's gone.
哦，不！
Oh, no!